<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Seasonable vvord, or, A word in season soberly proposed to the confederation of all such whose hearts are affected with those floods of reproach and blasphemy, which the cause of God in these nations labour under : and may serve, not only as a remembrancer of things past, (stammeringly hinted at) and a call to repentance for mis-improvement thereof : but may prove, a word of encouragement to some whose hands may be weakned in the faith and hope of the work of this day, Psalm 78.7.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B29579</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12927180</idno>
  <idno type="VID">200402</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264187800</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2250</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12927180</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B29579)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 200402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 990:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Seasonable vvord, or, A word in season soberly proposed to the confederation of all such whose hearts are affected with those floods of reproach and blasphemy, which the cause of God in these nations labour under : and may serve, not only as a remembrancer of things past, (stammeringly hinted at) and a call to repentance for mis-improvement thereof : but may prove, a word of encouragement to some whose hands may be weakned in the faith and hope of the work of this day, Psalm 78.7.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:200402:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:200402:1"/>
            <p>A Seasonable VVord, OR A VVORD IN SEASON: Soberly proposed to the Consideration of all such whose hearts are affected with those Floods of Reproach and Blasphemy, which the Cause of God in these Nations labours under. And may serve, not only as a Remembrancer of Things past, (stammeringly hinted at) and a Call to Repentance for mis-improvement thereof. But may prove, a Word of Encouragement to some whose Hands may be weakned in the Faith and Hope of the Work of this Day, <hi>Psalm</hi> 78.7.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MICAH 4.10, 11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Be in pain and labour to bring forth, O Daughter of Zion, like a Woman in Travail; Thou shalt dwell in the field, thou shalt go into Babylon, THERE shalt thou be delivered, THERE the Lord will Redeem thee from the hands of thine Enemies.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:200402:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:200402:2"/>
            <head>A Seasonable VVord, OR A VVord in Season: Soberly proposed to the Consideration of all such whose hearts are affected with those Floods of Reproach and Blasphemy, which the Cause of God in these Nations labours under.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen</hi> Israel <hi>went out of</hi> Egypt,<note place="margin">Psalm 114.</note>
               <hi>the House of</hi> Jacob <hi>from a People of a strange language:</hi> Judah <hi>was his Sanctuary, and</hi> Israel <hi>his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. The Sea saw it, and fled;</hi> Jordan <hi>was driven back. The Mountains skipped like Rams, and the little Hills like Lambs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When the Lord turned again the Captivity of</hi> Zion,<note place="margin">Psalm 126.</note> they <hi>were like men that dreamed. Then was</hi> their <hi>mouths filled with laughter, and</hi> their <hi>tongues with singing: among the Heathen it was said; the Lord hath done great things for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>These things</hi> (among others) <hi>happened to them for Ensam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> or types; <hi>and are written for our admonition,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.</note> upon whom
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:200402:3"/> the ends of the world are come:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 15.</note>
               <hi>That we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures, might have hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From a serious observation of the grand Mutations which have befallen in these Islands, who can but stand amazed, and wondering say, What hath God wrought?</p>
            <p>It is too evident and apparent, unto what a low-ebb the Cause of God in these Nations was brought, as it stood in the evidence and witness against <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Popish</hi> Innovations, (according to the measure of the Light which was then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated:) as also to what an heigth the Adversaries there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were arived, endeavouring by all possible means the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting and extirpation thereof, under the notion of <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanism;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide Basilicon Doron.</note> branding the Assertors thereof with terms of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, Puritans, Brownists,</hi> with other such like; Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition and prophaness countenanced and encouraged; and whoever in all this whole Nation durst depart from Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, made himself a prey, the dark Corners of our Earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of the habitations of Cruelty; the Whippings, Pillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Stigmatizing, Gagging, Banishing of some Persons (then eminent for their Testimony) are fresh in memory, which occasioned great and strong Cryes to be poured out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord night and day, that he would arise and visit his Remnant, and plead the Cause of his People, and set them at Liberty whom the wicked had snared; that he would break the jaws of the wicked, and pluck the spoil out of his teeth.</p>
            <p>And though the Kingdomes Liberties were greatly infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, yet the subject matter of those many Supplications which were put up to God, were for and on behalf of his Name, and People, in relation to their Soul-sufferings, which he most eminently had respect unto, and made it his concern to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the oppressors, and set the Captives free; taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and advantage from the very contrivances of the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, and in the very same matter wherein they intended to deal proudly and subtilly, he was above them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vide Mag Hist.</note>As in many other things, not now so particularly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred; the <hi>fatal Coal,</hi> (as a late Writer calls it) which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards became a great Fire in the three Kingdomes, (as then called) began to be kindled in the Year, 1637. by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:200402:3"/> upon the <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> about the <hi>Litturgy,</hi> which was then sent down thither under pretence to make a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Church Worship and Ecclesiastical Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> Prelacy being now Rampant and in its dignity, both here and there.</p>
            <p>But this Book of <hi>Litturgy,</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> or <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Masse Book;</hi> instead of effecting an Uniformity as was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,<note place="margin">☜</note> The <hi>Bishop</hi> who endeavoured to read it in his Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficalibus, was assaulted with Crickets, Stools, Sticks and Stones, from Men and Women, to the hazzard of his life; and from this poor contemptible disorderly Ryot or Mutiny, so accidentally happening, being in it self but a Cloud like an handbreadth, but had in it a noyse of much Rain; It was a Coal indeed raked up in embers, contemptible enough in its appearance, and one would have thought might have been easily quenched; but it appearing to be the House of <hi>Jacob,</hi> wherein this Coal was kindled, and the House of <hi>Joseph</hi> which thus became a flame; how should the House of <hi>Esau,</hi> who were but stubble, stand before devouring fire? as the sequel hath manifested.</p>
            <p>Hence it came to pass, that instead of quenching this fire the Nobility &amp; Ministry publickly avowed their detestation of that <hi>Book;</hi> and when it was re-inforced by a <hi>Proclamation</hi> at <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and the punishment of Treason denounced against the Persisters in the former proceedings; this also availed not to allay this heat, but the fire burnt hotter and hotter, as indeed well it might, for the Lord was in this fire.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Proclamation</hi> was accosted by a Protestation of the Nobility, Ministry, and others of that Nation, which grew suddenly into a solemn Covenant, for defence of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liberties, which begat no small rage in the Author of that <hi>Proclamation,</hi> but it availed not: thus this fire began, brake forth, and continued.</p>
            <p>Further endeavours were used for the dawbing of it, but you know who kindled it, and it would not be put out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hambleton</hi> is sent down to <hi>Edenborough,</hi> to deal with the Covenanters to renounce their Covenant, but avails not; He causes <hi>Proclamation</hi> to be made, to forbear to press the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:200402:4"/> of the <hi>Service Book,</hi> but that would not now do the turn, the fire had got too much hold, the differences grew greater and greater.</p>
            <p>A War is designed, an Army raised to subdue the <hi>Scots,</hi> the Earle <hi>Arundel</hi> made General; but this threatned War pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not, but through mediation of some Lords on both sides,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>June</hi> 18. 1639.</note> a pacification was made and declared, <hi>June</hi> 18. 1639. and the Armies on both sides retreated home peaceably, and the fire seemed to be put out, but it was but raked up in the embers, <hi>for it was impossible,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> returning to <hi>London,</hi> after a short time changed his mind from his thoughts of peace, and commanded by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation</hi> the Paper which the <hi>Scots</hi> avowed to contain the Conditions of the Pacification, to be burnt by the hands of the Hang-man; Now the fire began to break out again.</p>
            <p>In <hi>December,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> propounds a <hi>Parliament,</hi> to begin in <hi>April</hi> following,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> April 13. 1640.</note> the People wonder! however on <hi>April</hi> 13. 1640. the <hi>Parliament</hi> began. Money is required, <hi>viz.</hi> twelve Subsidies, to go on with a designed. War against <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> divers Speeches were made against the grant of Subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, till they first had some grievances redrest, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, that the People had no reason to pay for a War which they desired not: however they took the Subsidies into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dissolved</hi> May 5.</note> but while they were debating, on the fifth of <hi>May</hi> they were dissolved.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless the Convocation of <hi>Divines</hi> (so called) they were continued, and made Canons, and imposed upon the Clergy the <hi>Oath Etcetera,</hi> so notoriously remarkable at that time and since.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bellum Episc.</note>The Clergy contributed great Sums of Money toward this War, so did the <hi>Papists;</hi> besides what other means was used for defraying the charge of this War; The Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> commanded in cheif.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Private Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers made Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</note>But of all things remarkable, this may not be forgotten, That the hearts of the Soldiers were turned against many of their Officers, and Commanders, and could not be brought to engage against the <hi>Scots;</hi> but on the contrary, they turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reformers in their passage to <hi>York,</hi> pulled down <hi>Popish</hi> Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:200402:4"/> brake down Rails, turned Altars into Communion Tables, for that in effect this proved no considerable War nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by mediation of some <hi>English</hi> Lords, this War was composed also upon Articles: and upon the desire of the same Lords, the <hi>King</hi> resolved to call a <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> to begin the 3d. of <hi>November,</hi> 1640. which he accordingly did: Now would not any one think, that this would have proved the perfect cure of all the former Malladies, &amp; that the fire so strangely begun in <hi>Scotland,</hi> would have been extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guisht by the moderation, as well as by the mediation of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> But the Lord having given it a commission it must burn, till all the House of <hi>Edom</hi> be devoured, and that there be none remaining of the House of <hi>Esau,</hi> for the Lord hath spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, <hi>Obad.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Upon the 3d. of <hi>November,</hi> 1640. Assembled a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which continued many years, (by some called the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> by others the <hi>dateless Parliament</hi>) being by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> continued, till they should by an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> be dissolved.</p>
            <p>In their beginning and progress, they were men to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, to see how they were acted.</p>
            <p>Our Souls were filled with amazement at the things which we saw the Lord by them was visibly doing for this poor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Nation, rendring it as a spectacle of astonishment to all our Borderers the neighbour Nations round about us, such was then our case, as that when we knew not what to do, nor what to desire to have done for us; yet having our eyes up to him, who leads the blind in wayes which they know not, we saw him apparently leading our <hi>Parliament,</hi> our Steers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, into untroden paths and wayes, putting them upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions unforeseen, unprojected, yea unthought of, fulfilling herein that good Word of his, <hi>Isa.</hi> 42.12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>In the Management of these Affairs, we were given to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand more distinctly and particularly (in observing the course the Lord took for us, in stating our Controversie,) that he was arisen in <hi>England</hi> also, as well as he had already begun in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to avenge the quarrel of his Covenant against An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist, and that he had set himself by way of eminency a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:200402:5"/> the two main Props of his Kingdome, <hi>viz. <hi>Heirarchy,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Heirarchy.</note> and <hi>Monarchy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monarchy.</note> as being his two main Posts and Pillars in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and such as by which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alts himself in his opposition against the Kingdome of Christ: and for as much as by those two, the <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of his People, both as Men and Christians had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great violation, the Cry of the Oppressed as under both considerations had found access unto him, and he was come down to deliver them; In the prosecution whereof, he furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed his People with some lesser measures of light and spirit for his work, encouraging their hearts, and strengthening their hands; as well <hi>Representors,</hi> as <hi>Represented,</hi> taking into his work the hearts and hands, lives and estates of men as men, causing herein that word to be fulfilled, <hi>(viz. The earth to help the Woman,)</hi> each one in measure prosecuting his intrest, and concernment, (as the History of our Times will declare) Though therein also the counsel of the Lord lay deeper than the appearance.</p>
            <p>As touching the former of these, <hi>viz. <hi>Heirarchy,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Heirarchy.</note> how wonderfully did the Lord set himself against it, by causing to be detected the prophane and scandalous, corrupted and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting <hi>Clergy,</hi> beginning at the Toes and Feet, Claws and Feathers of this fowl Beast,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> Century of Scandalous Ministers.</note> in so much that whole Centuries of them were cast out as abominable Branches; Nor did he cease there, till he had made the head of this <hi>Hydra,</hi> or many headed Beast, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Prelates,</hi> who although they had built their nests amongst the Stars, and seemed to be out of reach of human power; yet even these he made to tumble themselves down headlong, and they fell as lightening from Heaven, cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves out from their Seats as untimely fruit, by their aspiring Vote; when (besides those who were Impeached for their personal Crimes) so many of them were expung'd the House of <hi>Peers,</hi> even by occasion of that very Vote, whereby they purposed to have establisht themselves in their <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary</hi> Capacity, as some time before they endeavoured to have done in their Convocation, by their monstrous <hi>Etcetera Oath:</hi> but in both Capacities, <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiastical,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they thought to have dealt subtilly and proudly, the Lord was above them.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:200402:5"/>
            <p>Who could have thought that ever the most high God had had such a work to have effected in our dayes, until we saw it done? We expected that it should have proceeded from the <hi>Smectymnians,</hi> but the Lord found out another way,<note place="margin">Psalm 9.16.</note> even by the work of their own hands, <hi>Higgaion, Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus God brought down this high Tree, Root and Branch, so far as it stood in visible opposition to the Kingdome of Christ; not only by detecting the Scandalous and Prophane, by parcel and piece-meal; but set himself against the whole body and headship of the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> by necessitating the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> to the utter abolishing thereof, and engaging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seles and the whole People of the Land by Covenant against it: <hi>And added to this,</hi> he caused this Scarlet couloured Harlot to be whipt and stript, by bringing upon the <hi>Parliament</hi> a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity to expose the Lands formerly appropriated to Bishops, Deans and Chapters, to sale, and to be distributed among the People: Thus making bare her skirts and rendring her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovely, fulfilling in some measure that word of Prophesie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. These shall <hi>hate the Whore, and make her desolate and naked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was this all, but <hi>Monarchy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monarchy</note> it self, that grand capital Corner Stone of the Kingdome of Antichrist (upon which the former did depend) against this also did the Eternal and most high God set himself, and gave his People light and faith in this work (causing it to spring up out of obscurity:) And through many difficulties led them on from step to step, and made them follow him in paths wherein he had himself first trod, thereby to bring about his work, his strange work, far above the expectations of his People, whom he imployed in effecting thereof;</p>
            <p>For as much as the <hi>Parliament,</hi> being (at the utmost) but affected with the common grievances of the Nations, as men spirited for that work, endeavoured the obtaining remedy therein, as their ultimate end; and certainly they would have acquiesced, if once they could have arrived at it, applying themselves accordingly for removing thereof;</p>
            <p>In all their Addresses to the <hi>Monarch,</hi> distinguishing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him &amp; his <hi>evil Council,</hi> endeavouring to render him free
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:200402:6"/> from any culp or blame: yet the most High (having other ends above the sight and reach of men) mingled a perverse spirit in him and his <hi>Counsellours,</hi> hardening his and their hearts (in order to his further work) insomuch that he was not suffered to hearken to the just complaints presented by the <hi>Parliament</hi> on behalf of the People, but became obstinate to his and their ruin, who adhered unto him; suffering him to withdraw himself from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to raise Force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, endeavouring thereby to repel their just de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            <p>The Controversie came to be stated, and the Peoples rights asserted under these three general Heads, among others, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>The Power of Levying Money.</item>
                  <item>The Power of the <hi>Militia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Negative Voyce.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The issue whereof was the total Defeat of his Forces, after several signal Battels, together with that wonderful Act of justice done upon himself, thereby bringing down this high Tree also, not only in his own Person, as a <hi>Monarch</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for his personal transactions, but also <hi>Monarchy</hi> it self; whence proceeded those <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament, Jan.</hi> 30. <hi>March</hi> 17. <hi>and</hi> 19. 1648. and <hi>May</hi> 19. 1649.</p>
            <p>By all which the Power became the Peoples, and a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was laid for a Free-State or Common-wealth, without a King, single Person, or House of Peers; and the People en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in pursuance of their late Conquest, to pursue and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the same accordingly: Adding further the exposing to sale, the Revenue formerly appropriated to the Office of King-ship, having first rendred the same Office Unnecessary, Chargeable, and Dangerous.</p>
            <p>Object. But if any should Object, <hi>That these Actions were but the issue of force and fraud, and are not to be justified as Parliamentary, and therefore that it is not safe to entitle God thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It may be Answered, That had it been only the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Consultation and Resolution, there might have remained some doubt upon the hearts of some, (though others were more clear therein.)</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:200402:6"/>
            <p>But to make it evident to all persons, that it was not the divice of man, nor the effect of his contrivance, but the arm and power of God: It will be necessary to consider besides what hath been already expressed, (touching the rise and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress of those wonderful mutations) how marvelously the same hath been confirmed by remarkeable and signal testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, such as may not, ye cannot be denyed by any man; our enemies themselves being judges; not to mention all those me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Series of transactions both by Land and Sea, as well in <hi>Ireland</hi> as in <hi>England,</hi> from and after the Year, 1648. nor the sharp conflict with <hi>Hollander,</hi> nor the issues thereof, wherein the Lord so manifestly appeared to the silencing of the adversary, that he extorted acknowledgments from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, while he made them say in these or the like words; What God is like the God of <hi>England?</hi> What God like the God of the <hi>Round-heads?</hi> according to that saying, <hi>Psal.</hi> 126.2. <hi>Then said they among the heathen, the Lord hath done great things for them:</hi> But,</p>
            <p>To reduce much into a little, let be remembred those two notable eminent and remarkeable contests, the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Forces had with the <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Dunbar</hi> and at <hi>Worcester,</hi> that by the mouth of these two witnesses instead of many more, this assertion may be establisht.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Scots</hi> (in order to the re-investing the Son of the late King, and in him to have re-established <hi>Monarchy</hi>) at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the effecting thereof by force of arms, it is well known that after solemn appeals to God for decision of the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie between the two nations, wherein not singly the person of the Son of the late King, nor the family of the <hi>Stewarts</hi> was the ground of the quarrel, but <hi>Monarchy</hi> it self, as appears by the Declaration of the Army at their marching into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the year 1650. wherein among other things they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, <hi>That they fought against</hi> Monarchy, <hi>as being perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their consciences that it was one of the ten horns of the Beast.</hi> And say further in the same declaration unto the <hi>Scots, viz. That if they shall proceed to bring in such a Government as one</hi> Man <hi>or</hi> King <hi>upon us, they will blot out the memory of their former merrits.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:200402:7"/>
            <p>Upon this state of the difference, they on both sides made their appeals to God; who was pleased to decide the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versy, and gave issue, for and on behalfe of the weak, the faint,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1650</note> and the feeble; against the mighty, the strong, and the valiant, in that notable conflict at <hi>Dunbar, Sept,</hi> 3. 1650.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Add further,</hi> That when the same cause was prosecuted by the <hi>Scots</hi> a second time upon their march into <hi>England,</hi> by the contrivance &amp; assistance of such as were confederate with them in that undertakeing; how did the Almighty appear for,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 2651</note> and on behalfe of his cause and people at <hi>Worcester;</hi> and added a further rebuke and discomfiture to <hi>Monarchy</hi> it felf, (which at that time also was about to be re-inforced) making an irrepairable breach upon the adversary, as the history of that period of time, more at large will explicate.</p>
            <p>Not only in those two eminent cases, wherein he who runs may read the finger of God as clearly against <hi>Monarchy,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore against <hi>Hierarchy;</hi> but ever since those times notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing there hath been a starting aside and a departure from those blessed footsteps of God, in not following fully to know &amp; do his further will: but strong inclinations, yea and as strong attempts and endeavours also to go back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> hancker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the onyons and garlick thereof; hastning to lay the foundation and to rear the superstructure of the ruined wals of <hi>Jericho,</hi> which God had so signally blasted with a curse to him and his seed, who should attempt the rebuilding thereof, in the person and family of the once famous and renowned General of the <hi>English</hi> Armyes; laying I say the foundation for <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> under the disguise of a <hi>Protector,</hi> and an high Commission Court of Tryers, &amp;c. which must have proved in short time a King and Prelates; to which were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that which followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> an House of <hi>Peeres,</hi> with much more of like—</p>
            <p>Yet these all received a seasonable rebuke from the Lord who in due time caused them to melt away as a snail; or as the untimely birth of a woman that might not see the Sun, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the pots could feel the thorns, he took them away by a whirlewind, seasonably in due time; and as it pleased him in the midst of their blasphemous <hi>Hosannaes:</hi> Upon the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:200402:7"/> considering what disappointments have attended all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, both of force and fraud which have been exercised to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the re-erecting the Throne of the Beast in <hi>England;</hi> in those two notable branches above recited, so eminently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared against by God, as being the great posts and pillars of Antichrist.</p>
            <p>As it is a confirmation of the truth asserted, so it is a ground of future expectation, that God will cause his own work to revive in the midst of the day of this great rebuke and blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, which his name, people, and cause, are exposed unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The long or dateless Parliament</hi> (so called) (which begun in <hi>November</hi> 1640. and by which so many memorable things had been transacted,) having been inturrupted, and disconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued six years and upwards, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>April</hi> 20. 1653. to <hi>May</hi> the 7. 1659: by the <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> were now after many debates, and much agitation in order to a future settlement, Invited by the same <hi>Army</hi> to return to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of their trust; who accordingly did so upon the 7th. of <hi>May</hi> as above, to the great comfort and satisfaction of many, whose eyes and hearts were upon them for good, expecting some wonderful and notable thing to be the issue of this strange and unexpected revolution; that having been as men free among the dead, they were certainly now anointed for some signal service, and that the work of the Lord which had as the Sun upon the dyal of <hi>Ahaz</hi> gon back so many degrees; would now be revived, and that Justice and righteousness would henceforth dwell in our land: This hopeful expectation was strengthned, not only by theit brief yet pyous declaration, but a Resolve which was made on the ninth of <hi>May;</hi> which cheared the hearts of many, hoping that the time was now come wherein all that truly feared God without partiality should be countenanced and encouraged, and called out of their holes, into which they were either forcibly driven, or had voluntarily retired themselves, during the interval of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> interruption: But alass these hopes soon va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, for a few dayes discovered, that neither the <hi>Army</hi> had right ends in inviting the <hi>Parliament</hi> to return; nor that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:200402:8"/> the <hi>Parliament</hi> was so resolved upon a speedy settlement of the <hi>Nations,</hi> as their necessity required, nor were so faithful to their own declaration and resolve, as was expected.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Lord to awaken both <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> stirred up the spirit of the Nation against them by that general insurrection intended from all quarters, but distinguished by the name of Sir <hi>George Booths</hi> insurrection, which was the only party that appeared, but was as soon disperst, and supprest by a parry of the <hi>Army,</hi> with very small and inconsiderable losse of men on either side; insomuch that it was reputed a bloodless victory: God hereby shewing what he could do in enlarging or restrayning the spirit of the Nation as he pleased: The effect of this dispensation was so far from improving ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>Army</hi> in the furthering of the settelment expected, that it produced a quite contrary effect; for upon the return of the Brigarde from the pursute of <hi>Sr. George Booth,</hi> they propose the setling of the conduct of the <hi>Army</hi> in the hands of General Officers: The <hi>Parliament</hi> on the contrary resolve to be <hi>General</hi> themselves, and to give Commissions with limitations; this begets dissatisfaction, and jealousie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> declares the Lord <hi>Lamberts</hi> Commission void, with eight other <hi>Field</hi> Officers, and settles Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the government of the <hi>Army,</hi> from <hi>October</hi> 11 to <hi>Feb.</hi> 12. 1659. Hereupon the <hi>Parliament</hi> becomes again to be interupted by the Army, and so remained from the 12th. of <hi>October</hi> to the 26th of <hi>December</hi> following, during which intervail, many agitations were used for their restoration, by vertue of the powers vested in the new <hi>Commissioners</hi> for the Army, some of them going to <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> and from thence influencing some part of the Army; the Fleet declaring for their restoration, and the Forces in <hi>Scotland</hi> doing the like, they returned with a very high hand upon the 26th. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1659. Being thus returned they soon fell upon changing the conduct of the Army, not only confirming their resolution, touching the nine Officers as before, but made a very great progress towards all such as had any way abetted, and assisted in their interruptions, putting from them with great severity all or most of their true interested and engaged friends against the common adversaries.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:200402:8"/>
            <p>Thus strangely and wonderfully hath God wrought in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking the pride and Apostacy of the Army, who having been unsteadfast in their declared and avowed resolutions, so so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly made, and so often repeated: the just and holy God hath in his due time called it to remembrance, and caused it to be returned upon them; even by those very persons over whom they thought they had power.</p>
            <p>Nor was the condition of the <hi>Parliament</hi> at all better by this transaction, for that very Spirit wich they raised to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press this of the Army, was too great for them to allay: but as apparently over-grew them, as theirs did that of the Army, and that also for want of those whom they had unnecessarily put from them.</p>
            <p>For the interest of the (so long) Secluded Members, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan now effectually to revive, and they by the assistance of the Army which came out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were brought into the House, who for want of an <hi>English</hi> Army, could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be kept out.</p>
            <p>And by the access of these later Members, their period was hastened, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> dissolved by an Act. Thus hath it happened through the overruling power of God, that fire is gone out from <hi>Abimalech,</hi> and hath devoured the men of <hi>Shechem,</hi> as fire came forth from the men of <hi>Shechem,</hi> and devoured the houshold of <hi>Abimalech;</hi> so true is that word, <hi>Psal.</hi> 9.16. <hi>The Lord is known by the Judgment which he executeth, the wicked is snared in the work of his own hands, Higgaion Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But by this means the cause of God, and of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in these Nations is wholly lost, and an opportunity is given to the enemy to blaspheme his name, and to say, where is now your God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It is true, that this day is a day of great rebuke and blasphemy, and it's as true that the people upon whom Gods name hath been named, have very much contributed thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, whether we respect the <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>Army,</hi> or the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons who have been influenced by both, <hi>Conjunctim aut Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sim:</hi> Who ever shall take a view of the transactions of affairs from, and after that signal battel fought in the Year, 1651.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:200402:9"/> the issue whereof was by the then general stiled, <hi>The marvai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Salvation wrought at Worcester;</hi> at which time, it might have been expected that the fruit thereof, could not have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved other than holiness unto the Lord, and justice and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness to the Nation; 'tis true indeed, the blame was laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that they improved not the mercies and deliverances God had given to the Nation by their means, and they were worthy of blame before the Lord, who to rebuke their remisness let loose that Spirit upon them which gave them their first interruption, in the Year, 1653. though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a more plausible pretence than the effect manifested, for as much as that <hi>Parliament</hi> being then removed from being a let as was pretended, who could have thought but that now righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness would have ascended the Throne, and whatsoever had been amiss in the former, would have been corrected and amended in this latter Edition; but it was too evident that the change was not for the better but for the worse, as the next succeeding (almost six years time will evidence,) how were all the former mercies and deliverances which God had wrought for this Nation, and his people therein wholly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by the power and influence of the Army; who set up their General as single Person, and chief Magistrate contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their own Declarations and solemn engagements therein, and thereby departing from their faith, breaking their own Bonds, and casting their Coards behind them, wherewith they had voluntarily bound and oblidged themselves. And this not as a transcient Act forcibly or fraudulently extorted from them, but by a Series of transactions renewed and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Father to the Son, to whom they became more solemnly devoted if possible, than they had been to the Father, this being a creature of their own forming; which evidently declares they did not account themselves surprized in their first compliance, for if so, they would never have made their bonds stronger by renewing their Oaths and Obligations undesired and unsought for.</p>
            <p>But as well it prospered, and as long it lasted, and as true were they to their last as to their former Oaths, they take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to destroy the creature of their own creating, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:200402:9"/> they had engaged to live and die with him: All which actings of their God hath brought upon their own heads, as well Army as <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the friends and allies of both, rejecting all our confidences which were placed in either of them.</p>
            <p>And although shame and confusion of face belongs to us, and unto those on whom we have leaned, who have proved to us, (especially of latter times) but <hi>Egyptian</hi> reeds on whom while we have leaned, they have pierced into our hand, and now we are ashamed of our confidences, and of those on whom we have (too much) depended: and must say, the Lord our God hath put us to silence, and given us the water of gall to drink, because we have sinned against him; and this is it while we hear the enemy blaspheming daily, saying, where is now their God?</p>
            <p>Nevertheless we know the foundation of the Lord stands sure, and with him is no variableness nor shadow of change; And though we must bear this present rebuke from the Lord, because we have sinned against him, yet he will arise and plead our cause; and cause his work to revive in the midst of the day of this rebuke and blasphemy; yea though for our unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness, and the unworthiness of our Rulers, <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary,</hi> and for their and our non-improvement of our mercies and deliverances, he may justly turn us down to the place of Dragons, &amp; suffer our carcasses to fall in the wilderness where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are wandring, and make us know what we have done in not following on to know him, whose goings forth are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as the morning: yet seeing he hath not left himself with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out witness, in that he hath frustrated all the attempts both se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and open, and not permitted any project or divice which hath been set on foot toward the bringing back his work, to prosper, though there have been many (and they also) crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrived, and vigorously prosecuted, yet their drivings have been like the drivings of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chariot, very heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with seasonable disappointments: what remains then, but that we humble our selves under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt us in due time, as knowing that although we have been yea, and nay, yet our God is yea; who when we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:200402:10"/> have born and accepted of the punishment of our Iniquity, he will not cast away nor abhor his remnant to destroy them ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, but in measure he will debate with them; for the Lord will judge his People, and repent himself for his Servants, when he seeth their (hand) or power is gone, and there is none shut up or left: Therefore what he said in another case, <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.24. to the King of the Children of <hi>Ammon, That which thy God Chemosh gives thee, wilt thou not possess?</hi> So whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever the Lord our God shall drive out from before us, them will we possess: So must we say in like case, we dare not be so untrue unto our God, the true and living God, as not to assert with all humble boldness, (yet with Christian Courage and Confidence) the intrest and right we have in what our God hath given us, both as Men and Christians, as the fruit of much Blood and Treasure, which he suffered not to be spilt and spent for nought, or as a thing in vain; when so many dear and precious to him, and as Instruments in his hand for the purchasing and obtaining thereof, have sacrificed their lives in the high places of the Field.</p>
            <p>Wherefore seeing God hath honoured us with giving and confirming to us, a glimpse of, and an entrance into our <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> Liberties, both as Men and as Christians, in freeing us from <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> above and beyond our thoughts, and contrivance or projection, and kept them down from their seats thus long, notwithstanding their strong endeavours to be peeping and creeping up under hidden forms and guises; yea seeing he hath laid the Axe to the root of both these Oaks of <hi>Bashan,</hi> and hewen them down, making useless and ineffectual all the endeavours which have been hitherto for the re-establishing the Old, or suffering the New dignised Plants to take root and grow, but followed them with succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive disappointments.</p>
            <p>Let us in all humble Reverence fall down before him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing our iniquity, and the iniquity of our Leaders, and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, praying that our and their sins may be pardoned and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; and then say with an holy and humble confidence, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, Awake, put on strength O Arm of the Lord, Awake as in the dayes of old; Art thou not it that hath cut</hi> Rahab, <hi>and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:200402:10"/> wounded the Dragon? We will remember thee from the Land of</hi> Jordan, <hi>and of the</hi> Hermonites, <hi>and from the Hill</hi> Missar: And though we are apt to say, <hi>Oh Lord, by whom shall</hi> Jacob <hi>arise, for he is small?</hi> Yet dare we not <hi>say a confederacy with them who say a confederacy;</hi> nor may we <hi>fear their fear, nor be afraid; The Lord of Hosts is with us, the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>is our refuge; who though he hath smitten us, will revive us, and we shall live in his sight, Maugre all the malice and rage of the enemy: The works of the Lord are great, sought out of all those who take pleasure therein.</hi> What therefore he hath, so signally owned, we must own, and cannot do other, till he himself cut off the entail of our hopes and confidences, which we understand is not otherwise to be done, than by giving te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony against the same Cause in the Contest, if ever it come to be cast upon him for decision by an Appeal; which it is humbly prayed he would in mercy prevent, if he so please; and let all his People say, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psalm 107.43.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whoso is wise, and will observe these things, even they shall understand the loving kindness of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>